Chiluba Sarah, Banda ICT Security Officer Result driven ICT Security Officer with 7 years' experience in ICT Infrastructure, Software development, Support and Security, seeking to use my script and problem solving skills to improve cost and performance. At the University of Zambia I saved 90% of overtime costs paid to accounts officers through automated processes.

Personal Details

Address:

Lusaka, Zambia

Phone Number:

+260 979294791

+260 760431080

Email Address:

chilubalungu42@gmail.com

LinkedIn Profile:

https://www.linkedin.com/in/chiluba-sarah-banda-b32005217

Skills

Excellent Research Skills

• • • •

Communication Skills



Problem solving

• • • •

Collaboration

 \bullet \bullet \bullet \bullet

Analytical

• • • • •

Project Management

 \bullet \bullet \bullet \bullet

Attention to detail

• • • • •

Prioritization

 \bullet

Work Experience

The Copperbelt University / ICT Security Officer

JAN 2021 - PRESENT, KITWE

- Participated in the production of business requirement analysis and proposal document for National Water Supply and Sanitation Council (NWASCO) System.
- Develops quality assurance and testing techniques and strategies during Software Development Life Cycle for institutional projects including Tax Online, ERB and EIZ.
- Developed a security standard document for the institution to ensure developers follow security best practices to produce secure systems.
- Ensures that developed system features and processes meet user requirements including Customs' systems.
- Communicates issues with project team such as developers, project officers and Technical leads to resolve any system issues.
- Documents all tests, defects, bugs, fixes and system enhancements.
- Resolves about 99% escalated issues on assigned systems.

The University of Zambia / System Support Officer

MAY 2015 - DEC 2020, LUSAKA

- Provided first and second level application support to ensure smooth operations.
- Managed and maintained 100% security of MySQL server databases for accounting system.
- Managed backups and disaster recovery plans for ACCSYS PeopleWare payroll and Sage EPR 1000 Accounting System for business continuity.
- Provided business requirements for the institution accounting system and developed a customized merge implementation for efficiency.
- Provided training and coaching to over 80 system users and new employees.
- Managed user accounts by granting access rights and privileges to only allow authorized system users.
- Managed Sage EPR 1000 Accounting system by clearing 99% errors relating bank reconciliations, general ledger posting, accounts payables and all the accounting modules.

Volunteer

2018-Present

Co-founder \$ Consultant

Village Banking

- •Designing and developing an automated system for efficiency and transparency.
- •Successfully managing records and leading 5 village banking groups with about 200 members.
- •Conducting monthly meetings and presentations for the group's success.
- •Constantly researching on business opportunities to empower group members.
- •Drafting constitution and performing calculations on savings and interests earned.

Awards

May 2012

The Zambia Federation of Employers/ Labor Day Award

 Awarded a Labor Day award for being dependable and dedicated to duty

Interests

- Women Empowerment
- Research
- Regional Development

The University of Zambia / Payroll Records Clerk

DEC 2010 - APRIL 2015, LUSAKA

- Maintained 100% efficiency for large record volume organization using Microsoft Access database.
- Assisted with typing, data entry and answering incoming calls and emails as required.
- Prepared and filed NAPSA returns on time for temporal employees to ensure compliance and payments are done before due date.
- Followed confidentially regulations to maintain privacy.
- Offered ICT and technical support to Accounting personnel including hardware repair and maintenance.
- Participated in training and other learning opportunities to expand knowledge such Records Management System.
- Improved physical and digital filing system with enhancements to organizational strategies.
- Prepared and posted inputs into payroll system. Prepared all DDAC payments –salaries, terminal benefits and any other payments and allowances with 100% accuracy.
- Automated most of the processes on payroll and reduced 90% of overtime allowances that was being paid to payroll staff.

Education

University of Greenwich-/BSc (Hons) Computer System & Networking JUNE 2016 - JULY 2018, *CYBER ACADEMY-LUSAKA*

• Graduated with Honors degree in Computer Systems and Networking

IMIS/BCS / Higher Diploma in Management of Information Systems JAN 2014 - JULY 2016, *CYBER ACADEMY-LUSAKA*

• Graduated with Higher Diploma in Management of Information Systems

DISP / Diploma in Information Systems and Programming JAN 2011 - JULY 2012, *NIPA-LUSAKA*

• Graduated with Diploma in Management of Information Systems and Programming